At the beginning of the 8th [music]
century, Spain was governed by Visigoth
kings for 300 years.
In 711, an Islamic army crossed the
channel separating North Africa from the
Iberian Peninsula and started an
invasion that forever changed Spain's
geographical and cultural landscape.
During the 8th century historians call
the Islamic Golden Age,
>> [music]
>> the Muslims erected imposing fortresses
and spectacular mosques.
They reorganized cities and built
luxurious gardens.
>> [music]
>> When flying over Spain today, we can
still see the remains that testify to
the Muslim influence in the Iberian
landscape.
Professor Susana Calvo Capilla is an
expert in history and Islamic
architecture.
>> Clear prop.
>> She studied many archaeological sites
around the Mediterranean Sea, but she's
now focused on Al-Andalus. This period
in Spanish history [music]
during which the Muslims dominated
almost all of the Iberian Peninsula.
>> Are you ready?
>> Yes.
>> Let's go.
>> Today, Susana is about to discover this
period of time's milestones from a new
angle.
It's quite an experience to watch these
expanses of land and to discover
Al-Andalus' history from above. I'm a
bit shaken by the wind.
Less than a century after the Prophet
Muhammad's death, the Muslims conquered
lands from Central Asia to [music] North
Africa.
On April 29th, 711, the chief of the
Muslim Umayyad army, Tariq ibn Ziyad,
[music]
and some 7,000 riders arrived on the
Strait of Gibraltar's coasts, determined
to defeat the Visigoth king Roderic.
It's moving to see Jabal Tariq. This
mountain was named Tariq after the first
leader of the Berber troops who crossed
the strait.
This strait was an entryway for all
cultures into the peninsula, and in 711,
it was once again the entryway for this
new culture that thrived in the
peninsula for eight centuries.
At the time, the Visigoth kingdom
dominating Spain was weakened by
corruption and conflicts between its
rulers.
While King Roderic and his troops were
busy repressing revolts in the north of
the peninsula, the Muslims attacked.
Although they were few, Tariq ibn
Ziyad's men quickly shattered the
Visigoth resistance
>> [music]
>> and took control of a small city,
Algeciras.
>> Algeciras comes from the Arabic
Al-Jazirat al-Khadra, meaning the Green
Island.
This is one of the first places where
Arab and Berber troops settled and made
a sort of camp.
And there, they had one of their first
prayers in a place that we don't know
much about, but that was later called
the Mosque of Las Banderas.
>> From the city of Algeciras, Tariq ibn
Ziyad's troops started [music] to
conquer the peninsula along the south
coast.
In July 711, they crushed King Roderic
and his men in the Andalusian
countryside during the Battle of
Guadalete. [music]
The Visigoths lost their leader.
Tariq ibn Ziyad and his army went up
north taking one city after the other.
Nearly 7 years after arriving in
Gibraltar, the Muslims extended the
Umayyad Caliphate [music]
to nearly all the peninsula that they
then named Al-Andalus, an Arabization of
the Visigoth name for Spain.
As the new masters of a land that was
completely foreign to them, the Muslims
imposed their culture, which was
transcribed in the architecture.
Toledo, the former Visigoth capital,
became one of the most important power
centers of Al-Andalus.
>> From above, you can clearly see why the
city was chosen as the capital multiple
times.
In fact, it has a totally strategic
localization with the river nearby, like
a ring.
To leave their mark on the city, [music]
the Muslims built a fort, erected
mosques, and created a labyrinth of
streets.
They also showed tolerance by allowing
the people to freely practice their
faith.
Here you can see the small alleyways,
tiny ones with houses close to one
another. This was the Jewish district.
Now known as the city of three cultures,
in the middle of the 8th century, Toledo
saw Muslims, Jews, and Christians
cohabit.
>> [music]
>> Despite tensions, intellectuals and
Muslim scholars flocked there.
The city became one of Al-Andalus's most
important cultural and religious
centers.
>> [music]
>> One striking example of this
transformation is the Bab al-Mardum
Mosque.
Here we're at the city's north gate,
which is kind of the natural entryway
into the city because all around the
city there is the river.
Anyone who entered through this gate saw
the Bab al-Mardum Mosque with its double
arches and its white and red voussoirs.
It's a peculiar mosque, and it's not
like the others in the district because
it has a beautiful facade, while the
others are not as decorated.
Here we are inside the mosque.
What's surprising here is that you don't
see anything extraordinary on ground
level.
However, when you look up, you can see
that in each of these squares, in that
tiny oratory, there is a big cupola with
patterns that are intertwined and shaped
like stars.
It's probably what's most spectacular
about this place.
>> Like the model of the small mosques
erected in Toledo between the 8th and
the 11th century,
the Bab al-Mardum architecture was
designed for prayer and teaching.
>> If you look carefully, this
square-shaped room is very well adapted
for the teaching sessions given by the
mosque.
Usually, the teachers would teach while
leaning on a pillar, and the students
were sitting all around him.
You must imagine them surrounded by his
students, including his family, who
listened to his lessons.
>> Although they controlled the important
cities like Toledo,
the Umayyad Caliphate was undermined by
constant internal fights and had [music]
to face the Christian resistance in the
north of the territory.
In the middle [music] of the 8th
century, Christians extended the
Asturias kingdom, while the Muslims
dominated 70% of the southern peninsula.
During these unstable times, a new
leader appeared, the Andalusian falcon,
the prince Abd al-Rahman the 1st.
To mark his power in 756, he renamed
[music] the Umayyad Caliphate as the
Emirate of Cordoba.
>> Now we will travel south from Toledo
because although Toledo was an important
city of Al-Andalus,
all the capital cities of the emirate,
the Umayyad Caliphate, and their history
after that, were located in the south.
So now we're headed to Cordoba, the city
the Muslims chose as the capital for
strategic reasons because it allowed
them to control Baetica, a province that
covered the entire southern part of the
territory.
>> Around the 10th century, [music]
Cordoba became an independent Caliphate.
While Toledo and other prestigious
[music] cities waned, Cordoba was at the
height of its influence.
When flying over the city today,
>> [music]
>> we immediately notice the symbol of this
period full of splendor, the Great
Cordoba Mosque.
>> [bell]
>> Historian Carmen Gonzalez Gutierrez grew
up in Cordoba and has always been
fascinated by the Great Mosque's history
and architecture. [music]
>> It's a complex building because all the
keys of not only Cordoba's history, but
also Al-Andalus's history are hidden in
every tiny detail.
And that's why I'm still surprised every
time I see it.
>> [music]
>> According to ancient texts, at the end
century, the Great Mosque was built on
an ancient Visigoth church.
In the two centuries that followed,
rulers kept on extending [music] and
changing the building.
At the end of the 10th century, the
mosque had doubled in size [music] and
became the heart of Cordoba.
>> Cordoba became a court where the world's
wisest men gathered.
It allowed the progress of medicine, the
evolution of literature and philosophy.
All these arts and sciences started to
develop here.
This place is therefore a reflection of
a newly gained pride, different
politics.
>> The mosque was not only a place of
worship. It also had political, social,
and cultural purposes.
>> The mosque had a courtyard where many
activities took place.
Merchants would come to the mosque to
sell their products in the courtyard.
Judges would hold trials in the shade of
the porticoes when they didn't want to
hold them inside.
The courtyard was a part of the city
that was full of life.
>> [music]
>> The Great Mosque is now a Catholic place
of worship, but under the Umayyad
Caliphate, practicing Muslims gathered
under these majestic arcades.
Its architects [music]
built it out of granite, onyx, and
colored marble.
To give the prayer room more fullness,
they intertwined the horseshoe arches
that are supported by some 856 columns.
At the end of the prayer room is the
richly decorated mirhab.
>> As all Muslim people must look towards
Mecca, they look through here, and the
Caliphate knew it very well.
This place would become a display.
The Caliphate wrote down a series of
ideological messages that allowed him to
spread his propaganda.
That's why you can find some messages of
the Quran, a vegetal and symmetrical
decoration, very finely made, evoking
paradise.
For Muslims, paradise is a garden, an
orchard that's full of flowers and
plants, with water and a lot of shade.
>> For the Muslim princes, luxurious
gardens were a symbol of life after
death.
They were also a place to rest and
meditate. [music]
To create this impression of paradise on
earth, gardens were built all over the
territory.
One of these gardens can still be
visited a few miles from Cordoba, at the
bottom of Calif Abd al-Rahman the
third's city, Madinat al-Zahra.
Built in the middle of the 10th century,
these sophisticated gardens terraces
convey a peaceful setting.
Above all, they're a source [music] of
fertility, food, spices, and medicinal
herbs for the caliph's kitchens and
pharmacy.
The Muslim gardeners introduced [music]
the essence of plants and trees that
were until then absent from the
Al-Andalus land, cinnamon, artichokes,
[music] and watermelon.
They also brought their knowledge on
irrigation.
This mastery [music]
of agriculture still influences Spain
today.
300 miles east of Cordoba,
there's a vast expanse of greenhouses
all around the Mediterranean coast
region.
Meanwhile, the neighboring city of Elche
still contains Europe's biggest palm
grove.
>> Nuestra cultura in the
>> Our culture and identity, as well as
modern Spain's identity, must consider
this Islamic past.
>> Today, the Elche palm grove has more
than 70,000 date palm trees. Created by
the Carthaginians, then maintained by
the Romans, the Muslims made a vast
irrigation system between the 7th and
the 10th centuries, thus creating an
oasis in the heart of the city.
>> It's very interesting to see these
expanses from above and to imagine what
happened on these lands.
>> At the beginning of the 11th century,
plagued by civil wars, the Umayyad
dynasty was divided into multiple
hostile kingdoms called Taifas, among
which the Taifas of Toledo, Cordoba,
Seville, [music] and Granada.
At that time, [music] attacks from
Christian armies who came from the north
became more brutal and decisive.
To defend and protect the population,
[music]
the Taifa rulers erected imposing
fortifications around their cities.
185 mi south of the Elche palm grove,
there's one of these impressive
defensive structures at the top of a
hill that overlooks a small coastal
town,
Alcazaba of Almeria.
Further west, in the Andalusian
mountains, the city of Ronda has [music]
had an equally fast and extraordinary
transformation.
Jose Manuel Castaño Aguilar is an
archaeologist and specialist in the
history of this city with an exceptional
location.
>> What's most impressive about Ronda for
me
is seeing the city from the outside.
Because that's how you really appreciate
the fact that the city emerged from a
mountain cirque, the Serranía de Ronda.
If you had to name one of Ronda's
characteristics, you would say that it's
mainly a fortified city.
>> Under the Roman Empire, then the
Visigoths, the natural defense system
offered by these cliffs has always
attracted populations in search of
security.
When Ronda and its surroundings became
the seat of an independent [music] Taifa
in 1039,
its leaders decided to extend its city
walls.
Despite exceptional [music]
fortifications, in the middle of the
11th century, Ronda surrendered to the
Seville Taifa.
One century later, a new Islamic [music]
dynasty, the Almohads, took control of
nearly all the south of the peninsula.
>> Ronda's prime began in the Almohad
period.
Starting from an Islamic city,
a madinat already settled during the
Taifa era,
the Almohads kept on developing the city
by creating new suburban districts.
For example, the lower part of the city,
where the baths are currently located,
was created during the Almohad period.
What's certain is that the Almohads
brought their own way of organizing the
territory, which brought Ronda a renewed
notoriety.
This new status persisted until the
Nasrid period, at the end of medieval
times.
>> Ronda [music] isn't the only city which
underwent spectacular changes under the
Almohad dynasty.
60 mi further south, Al-Andalus' new
capital.
>> Now we'll go through Seville to see this
new capital, which in the 12th century
was embellished by the Almohads by a
series of important monuments.
>> [music]
>> In 1198, the new Almohad caliphate
finished building the symbol of its
power,
an imposing mosque, the minaret of which
culminates at 300 ft. Today it's called
the Giralda.
>> [music]
>> In the beginning [music] of the 13th
century, internal conflicts and constant
wars with Christian armies weakened the
Almohad dynasty.
A new leader emerged, Ibn al-Ahmar.
In 1232, [music]
he proclaimed himself Muhammad I,
chief of the Nasrid dynasty.
He settled in Granada and made it the
capital of his kingdom.
>> geographically, but also historically.
Granada was the last capital city of
Al-Andalus and its last kingdom.
It was the ending point of the economic,
artistic, and cultural splendor.
From above, it's a fascinating city
because there are different hills that
mark the places where power settled.
The Alhambra palaces that are on this
red hill, which is where the city got
its name from, are emblematic of the
Islamic culture in the peninsula.
>> Historian Barbara Boloix grew up in
Granada.
She spent a big part of her academic
career [music] studying this site in
every single detail.
>> You would need to empty the Alhambra
from tourists to imagine how life was
here in the Lions Palace.
This is where the Alhambra dynasty's
political and family life took place.
This is where the Sultan lived with his
spouses
and the court life took place.
We know the Sultan received the greatest
political figures of his time.
>> Originally, there used to be on the
Alhambra hills a small military base
built in 899
on the ruins of a Roman fort.
When Muhammad the first discovered the
site three centuries later,
he had a goal in mind.
>> The principal function of the Alhambra
was military. Muhammad the first looked
for a place where he could watch over
his entire territory. That's why you can
find a fort in the Alcazaba, a 360°
panoramic where one can watch over the
Vega territory and Granada's
surroundings.
In the 14th century, when the people
acknowledged the dynasty and the kingdom
was more stable, prosperity developed,
and allowed the construction of palaces.
From the outside, the Alhambra is a
sober assembly of cubes,
and so nothing indicates that inside
there is such a profusion of decor.
The sound of water, the vegetation, the
decoration,
these are elements that fill up our
senses.
Water had always been part of the
Islamic culture for its practical and
religious uses.
But for the Nasrid conceptors of the
Alhambra,
water was also used for its aesthetic
value.
It's a vast decorative program.
We say that the Alhambra is Arabic
poetry deluxe edition.
Inside the Alhambra,
you can obviously find a lot of
inscriptions in Arabic that are composed
of Quran extracts, which protect this
place.
So, they allow us to understand the
purpose of this place, political,
religious,
In the second half of the 15th century,
internal divisions weakened the Nasrid
dynasty.
Christian troops resumed their conquest
of land in all of Andalusia.
The fight led by the Nasrid to defend
the last bastion of their presence on
the Iberian Peninsula lasted 10 years.
The Alhambra was never attacked by armed
forces.
Some say the Alhambra surrendered at
night to prevent the inhabitants of
Granada from being scared.
The people was made aware of the
surrender the next morning when they
found the first Christian signs in the
palace.
That means that the last emir of the
Nasrid dynasty gave the keys of the
Alhambra to the Catholic Kings on July
the 2nd, 1492.
This is the end of the Nasrid kingdom as
well as Al-Andalus's history.
After eight centuries of domination on
the Iberian Peninsula, the last Islamic
kingdom of Occidental Europe
disappeared.
But signs of [music] this presence, the
rich cultural and artistic influence of
this civilization, are still visible in
today's Spain.
>> [music]
[music]